It is also worth looking at how the
White House has responded to the Mecca
Pact. President Trump not only refrained
from criticizing it, he praised it.
In Trump's worldview, the pact fits
neatly into his long-standing emphasis
on burden-sharing, US allies taking
greater responsibility for their own
defense and for regional security.
But, there is a fundamental problem with
that interpretation. Saudi Arabia,
Turkey, and Pakistan are assuming a
greater responsibility largely because
they have lost confidence in the
effectiveness of the American security
umbrella. For the signatories, the pact
is an additional insurance policy
against further US failures. Had
American guarantees worked as expected
during the war with Iran, the need for
such a regional mechanism would have
been far weaker.
Still, the United States is not about to
lose its position as the most powerful
military actor in the Middle East. What
it is gradually losing is its near
monopoly over the security architecture
of its regional partners.
As alternative arrangements develop,
Washington will find it harder to use
American protection as a source of
political leverage. Over time, that will
also reduce its influence over decisions
made across the region.